Guide to the Robert B. Fetter Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Robert Barclay Fetter papers
1978-1989
MS 1496
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.75
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, and itineraries which document the professional activities of Robert B. Fetter, especially throughout the 1980s. Many of the materials relate to Fetter's expertise in the field of health care management, and particularly to his innovations and work concerning Diagnosis Related Groups (DRGs). The papers include some files pertaining to Fetter's responsibilities within the Yale University School of Organization and Management.
Fetter, Robert B.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Robert B. Fetter, 1989.
Conditions Governing Access
This materials are mainly open for research, with some exceptions. Series I, boxes 1-2, is closed until 2009. Series III, box 8, is closed until 2007. Materials contained in Series V, box 10 is restricted until January 1, 2063 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, and itineraries which document the professional activities of Robert B. Fetter, especially throughout the 1980s. Many of the materials relate to Fetter's expertise in the field of health care management, and particularly to his innovations and work concerning Diagnosis Related Groups (DRGs). The papers include some files pertaining to Fetter's responsibilities within the Yale University School of Organization and Management. Forms part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection.
Biographical / Historical
Robert Barclay Fetter was born in Berwyn, Illinois, in 1924. In 1947, he was awarded a B.S. in Electrical Engineering from Virginia Polytechnic Institute. Afterward, he went on to receive both an M.B.A. and a D.B.A. from Indiana University, in 1949 and 1952, respectively. From 1953 to 1958 Fetter worked as an assistant professor of industrial management at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. In 1958, Fetter arrived at Yale University as an associate professor of industrial management, the first of a series of faculty and administrative posts he would assume at the university, including the Harold J. Hines, Jr. professorship in health care management and the chairmanship of the Yale University School of Organization and Management.
The professional accomplishment for which Fetter is most widely known is the development of Diagnosis Related Groups (DRGs), a conceptual framework which helps to define the "products" of a hospital. The DRG system identifies these products based on the characteristics of patients receiving comparable services. For Fetter, DRGs held the possibility of improving cost accounting, budgeting, and quality controls in hospitals. The application of DRGs in the United States, including their use as the basis of Medicare claims, led to international demand for more knowledge about their possibilities for hospitals in other parts of the world. Fetter's expertise in the development of DRGs regularly took him to meetings and conferences in different countries.
Fetter retired from the faculty at Yale in 1989.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. Correspondence, 1982-1989. II. Conferences and Workshops, 1978-1989. III. Yale University School of Organization and Management (SOM) Files, 1983-1986. IV. General Files, 1981-1989.
Diagnosis related groups; Health planning; Health services administration; Medical care; Fetter, Robert B.; Yale University. School of Management
- Correspondence, 1982-1989; Series I
  Conditions Governing Access
  The materials are open for research.
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence is organized chronologically and documents the Yale School of Organization and Management, Fetter's travel plans, meetings, reports, publications and some personal finance. Both directly and indirectly, much of the correspondence concerns Fetter's research on Diagnosis Related Groups (DRGs). There is some correspondence between Fetter and researchers and faculty at other institutions about his work. In addition, there are evaluations and comments by Fetter regarding articles written by others and submitted to journals for possible publication. Some of the letters also describe Fetter's association with the Henry J. Kaiser Foundation, as well as the Health Systems Management Group that existed for a time within the Yale School of Organization and Management.
  - Correspondence, 1982 May-1986 March (Box 1, Folder 1-14)
  - Correspondence, 1986 April-1989 March, undated (Box 2, Folder 15-29)
- Conference and Workshop Files, 1978-1988; Series II
  The conference and workshop files are arranged alphabetically by the institution primarily responsible for the meeting. They mostly contain materials relating to formal discussions and presentations on Diagnosis Related Groups (DRGs) and other aspects of hospital management. The files include Fetter's notes, outlines, and presentation materials. Pamphlets and brochures from the institutions themselves are often included as well.
  - Academy of Management, 1980-1988 (Box 3, Folder 1-8)
  - Alpha Bates, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Ambulatory Visits Group (AVG), 1989 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - American Association for Medical Systems and Informatics, Computer Applications in Medical Care (SCAMC), 1983 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - American Association of Professional Standards Review Organizations, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - American College of Physicians, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - American Convertors, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - American Federation of Clinical Research, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - American Hospital Association (AHA), 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 16-19)
  - American Institute for Decision Sciences (AIDS), 1979-1984 (Box 4, Folder 20-24)
  - American Institute of Industrial Engineers. Health Services Division (AIIE-HSD), 1982 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - American Medical Review Research Center, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - American Society of Mechanical Engineers, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Arizona State University, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Association of American Medical Colleges, 1980, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 29-30)
  - Blue Cross/Blue Shield of North Dakota, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Brandeis University
    - Ambulatory Care Project, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Health Policy Center Seminar, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Brigham and Women's Hospital and Harvard Medical School, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Daughters of Charity (Dallas, TX), 1983 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Downey Community Hospital, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Escuela de Alta Direccion y Administracion, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - European Conference on Operations Research
    - EURO V, 1982 July (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - EURO VI, 1983 July (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - European Institute for Advanced Studies in Management, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - French Ministry of Social Affairs/ Congress of Portuguese Hospital Administrators, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Greater New York Hospital Association, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Group Health Association of America, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences, 1983, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 44-45)
  - Health Care Financing Administration, Health and Human Services, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Health Data Management Association (HDM), 1986 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Healthcare Financial Management Association
    - Eastern Michigan Chapter, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Maryland Chapter, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Northeastern New York Chapter, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Henry Ford Hospital [Detroit, MI], 1984 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Hippocrate 2001, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Hospital Council of Eastern Pennsylvania, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Indiana State Medical Group Management Association, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Institute of Industrial Engineers, Hospital Management Systems Society, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Institute of Management Sciences (TIMS)
    - XXVI Conference, 1984 June (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - XXVII Conference, 1986 July (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - International Conference on System Science in Health Care, 1984, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 58-59)
  - International Economics of Health Care, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - International Medical Informatics Association (IMIA), 1988 (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - Management Services for Health, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - Medical Group Management Association (MGMA), 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 63-64)
  - Mercy Hospital [Urbana-Champaign, IL], 1983 (Box 6, Folder 65)
  - Mercy Hospital [Portland, ME], 1983 (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - Metropolitan Clinical Laboratories Ltd. [Vancouver, B.C.], 1986 (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - National Center for Health Statistics (NCHS), 1980, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 68-69)
  - National City Corporation [Cleveland, OH], 1985 (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - National Conference on Data Base Information Systems, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - National Institute of Mental Health, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - National Medical Enterprises, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - New Jersey, State Department of Health, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - Northwestern University, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Operations Research Society of America/ The Institute of Management Sciences (ORSA/TIMS), Visiting Lecturer's Program
    - General, 1978-1981, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 76-80)
    - Visiting Lecturer's Program
      - State University of New York at Albany, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 81)
      - University of Alabama at Birmingham, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 82)
  - Pfizer Presidents Forum [Carlsbad, CA], 1983 (Box 7, Folder 83)
  - Providence Hospital [Anchorage, AK], 1983 (Box 7, Folder 84)
  - Schering-Plough Conference, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 85)
  - Sisters of Charity of Leavenworth, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 86)
  - Sisters of Providence, Seattle, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 87)
  - Society for Computer Medicine, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 88)
  - Society for Hospital Planning, American Hospital Association, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 89)
  - St. Mary's Hospital [Rochester, MN], 1986 (Box 7, Folder 90)
  - Travenol Laboratories Ltd., 1984 (Box 7, Folder 91)
  - Tri-State Hospital Association, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 92)
  - University of Colorado. College of Business and Administration and Graduate School of Business Administration, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 93)
  - University of Illinois at Chicago. Hospital and Clinics, Hospital Management, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 94)
  - University of Michigan. Medical Center, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 95)
  - University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. School of Public Health, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 96)
  - Veterans Administration. Department of Medicine and Surgery, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 97)
  - William Beaumont Hospital [Royal Oak, MI], 1982 (Box 7, Folder 98)
  - World Association for Medical Informatics, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 99)
- Yale University School of Organization and Management Files, 1983-1986; Series III
  Arranged alphabetically by topic, most of these files relate to Fetter's work as a faculty member of the Yale University School of Organization and Management (SOM). The folder on Fetter's leave of absence documents some of his professional activities abroad. The files refer to SOM more in general terms than they do to Fetter's involvement in the school. The files are restricted until 2007.
  - Budget committee, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Computer committee, 1983-1985 (Box 8, Folder 2-3)
  - Faculty evaluations
    General
    See: Restricted,Box 10, Folder 1
  - Leave of absence, 1983-1985 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Program in Hospital Administration, Diagnosis Related Groups (DRGs) Conference, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Student evaluations
    General note
    See: Restricted, Box 10, Folder 2
    See:
  - Yale University Hospital Administration Alumni Association (YUHAAA), 1983 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- General Files, 1981-1989; Series IV
  General Files document some of Robert Fetter's professional activities other than formal conferences and workshops. The first folder, "Biographical," holds a curriculum vita which lists all of Fetter's major publications, from 1951 to 1988. The "Interviews" folders do not hold transcripts of Fetter's television appearances, but the "Your Practice" folder contains a working script and set of questions for the program that featured Fetter.
  - Biographical, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Central Connecticut State College [accreditation evaluation], 1981-1982 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - French language course, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Interviews
    - Healthcost Journal [television interview], 1987 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Your Practice [television interview on MDTV], 1984 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Restricted, 1982-1988; Series V
  Materials contained in this box is restricted until January 1, 2063 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
  - Faculty evaluations (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Open 2063 Jan
  - Student evaluations (Box 10, Folder 2)